A Guide to the Papers of John Carl Miller 1830-1979
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Carl Miller 1830-1979
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5218-g
This collection consists of six Hollinger boxes (2.5 linear shelf feet).
Horace Symonds
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a bequest of John Carl Miller, and was received by the Library on November 18, 1980.
Biographical/Historical Information
Miller was born in Escatawpa, Mississippi, in 1916. He recieved a B.A. degree in English from Millsaps College in Jackson, Mississippi, and later earned an M.A. (1947) and Ph.D. (1954) in English from the University of Virginia. Miller was a specialist in early American literature and an authority on Edgar Allan Poe. He taught at the University of Alabama, Louisiana State University, Bridgewater College, Bridgewater, Virginia, and the Virginia Military Institute before joining the faculty at Old Dominion University, Norfolk, Virginia, in 1967. He remained there until his death in October 1979.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists on six Hollinger boxes (ca. 2.5 linear shelf feet) the papers, 1830-1979, of John Carl Miller, an Edgar Allan Poe scholar.
The collection includes Miller's manuscripts of Poe's Helen Remembers and John Henry Ingram's Poe Collection at the University of Virginia; a typescript of John Henry Ingram's of "The True Story of Edgar Allan Poe," business papers associated with Miller's Building Poe Biography; and source material regarding Edgar Allan Poe, his family, and friends.
The material on Poe's Helen Remembers contains two copies of the typescript, one annotated, both with autograph corrections and miscellaneous pages; and an index. The dates of the two manuscript pages are unknown but the book itself was published in 1979 by The University Press of Virginia.
Miller then prepared a revision of his 1960 edition of John Henry Ingram's Poe Collection which was accepted for publication by The University Press of Virginia a month before his death. The material includes a typed manuscript, an index, and copies of working material, annotations and corrections.
The folders with materials related to Building Poe Biography, which was published by Louisiana State University Press in 1977, contain an index submitted for review, a typescript of "Review of Building Poe Biography", a contract, royalty statements, correspondence, invoices, canceled checks, and receipts. Louis Rubin is a correspondent.
There are ca. 775 pages of a carbon copy of a typescript of "The True Story of Edgar Allan Poe by John H. Ingram." a note on the title page states "This typescript made from the manuscript in 1954-1955 by John C. Miller." Three pages of autograph corrections and additions are included.
The Source Information regarding Edgar Allan Poe consists of copies of articles in at least twenty late 19th century newspapers and periodicals including Scribner's Monthly, The Athenaeum, New York Herald, Baltimore Sun, and Appleton's Journal. There are also copies of letters of F. W. Thomas to Poe and of John H. Ingram, Maria Poe Clemm, and Sarah Helen Whitman. In addition, this source material contains autograph notes and lists, photographs of Sarah Helen Witman, Edouard Manet's drawing of Poe and of the Providence (Rhode Island) Athenaeum Library, and a card file containing Miller's notes Poe's correspondence.
Organization
The collection has been divided into three series: I. Manuscripts, II. Business Papers, and III. Source Material. The manuscript series is arranged alphabetically and includes two manuscripts of Poe's Helen Remembers, one of John Henry Ingram's Poe Collection and one of The True Story of Edgar Allan Poe. The second series, Business Papers, was chiefly generated by the publication of Building Poe Biography". The third series contains the source material. Except as noted, the original organization of each series is unchanged. The original organization of the latter two series was not apparent. During the processing of the Source meterial, scattered unfoldered items were added to it and the items associated with Building Poe Biography were removed to create the Business Papers series.
Contents List
- I. Manuscripts
  - John Henry Ingram's Poe Collection, Revision of 1960 edition by John Carl Miller 1973, TMs (Box 1)
  - Index, John Henry Ingram's Poe Collection, 1960 edition, marked and annotated ca. 1973, TMs (electrostatic copy) (Box 1)
  - Poe's Helen Remembers, by John Carl Miller, w/autograph corrections and annotations [1979], TMs (electrostatic copy); 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Poe's Helen Remembers, by John Carl Miller, w/autograph corrections and annotations [1979], TMs (electrostatic copy); 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Poe's Helen Remembers, by John Carl Miller, w/autograph corrections [1979], TMs (electrostatic copy); 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Poe's Helen Remembers, by John Carl Miller, w/autograph correction [1979], TMs (electrostatic copy); 4 folders (Box 3)
  - "Index", Poe's Helen Remembers, by John Carl Miller, w/autograph corrections and typescript list of changes in index and text [1979], TMs (electrostatic) (Box 3)
  - Poe's Helen Remembers, by John Carl Miller, (miscellaneous notes), w/ autograph corrections and notes [1979], TMs (electrostatic copy) (Box 3)
  - Poe's Helen Remembers, John Carl Miller, w/autograph corrections and annotations (removed pages) [1979], TMs (electrostatic copy) (Box 3)
  - "The True Story of Edgar Allan Poe," by John H. Ingram, w/annotations and corrections by [Miller] 1954-1955, Carbon Typescript from MS; 5 folders (Box 4)
- II. Business Papers
  - Jarrett, Beverley: L. S. U. Press. TLS from Ms. Jarrett and electrostatic copy of John Miller's response concerning Building Poe Biography1977, 1978 (Box 4)
  - L. S. U. Press-Sales and Promotion-Correspondence, financial transactions, and advertising concerning Building Poe Biography 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - L. S. U. Press Advertisments, Vol. I, Building Poe Biography1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with L.S.U., University of Tennessee Press and others concerning Building Poe Biography 1967-1978 (Box 4)
  - Royalty statements and correspondence, L. S. U. Press concerning Building Poe Biography1977-1979 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and contract, L. S. U. Press 1968, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    re Building Poe Biography
  - Correspondence w/ Leslie E. Phillabaum, Associate Director and Editor L. S. U. Press 1974-1976 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence w/Louis D. Rubin, Jr. concerning Building Poe Biography 1968-1973 (Box 4)
  - Letter from L.S.U. Press enclosing "Index" for review. The "Index" is an electrostatic copy of a typescript of a Manuscript for Building Poe Biography1976 (Box 4)
  - "Reviews of Building Poe Biography," a list, corrected typescript, autographed by the author 1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with University Press of Virginia and corrected, electrostatic copy of "Bibliography of Books and Magazine articles published by John C. Miller" 1979, n.d. (Box 4)
- III. Source Material
  - Poe's Brain Petrified," electrostatic print of newsclipping 1878 (Box 5)
  - Poe and the Hall of Fame, electrostatic copies of newsclippings from Baltimore Sun1910 (Box 5)
  - "The Last Days of Edgar A. Poe"--S. A. T. Weiss, electrostatic clipping from Scribner's Monthly1878 (Box 5)
  - "Poe Reciting 'The Raven'"-- S. A. T. Weiss electrostatic clipping from Richmond Dispatch reprint from Scribners1878 (Box 5)
  - The Civil Service Review, Autograph notes and annotated typed card concerning Poe's Poems 1875, 1877 (Box 5)
  - The two burials of Poe, electrostatic copy of newclipping from ? News, Baltimore 1894 (Box 5)
  - "Poe's Unhappy Sister," electrostatic copy of newsclipping from The Sun, Baltimore 1905 (Box 5)
  - "The Woman Who Rejected Poe," Boston Herald, Photostatic copy of newsclipping 1909 Jan 17 (Box 5)
    re SHW's Portrait by John N. Arnold,
  - SHW's Letter to Mrs. Clemm, electrostatic copy of autograph, signed letter, and list of letter 1849 Oct 7 (Box 5)
  - EAP's Trial at West Point, electrostatic copies, proceedings and orders 1830, 1831, 1874, 1913 (Box 5)
  - N. Garnett to JHI 1884, ALS, electrostatic copies of letter (Box 5)
  - "Poe as seen by the brother of 'Annie'", electrostatic copy from New England Quarterly, article by F. W. Coburn 1943 (Box 5)
  - Rosalie Poe to John Ingram, electrostatic copy of autograph letter 1874 April 28 (Box 5)
  - Rosalie Poe to John Ingram, electrostatic copy of letter 1874 June 9 (Box 5)
  - "Disinterment of the Remains of Edgar A. Poe" [631], electrostatic copy of newsclipping ca. 1875 (Box 5)
  - Letters, numbers [60], [148], [169], [197], [297], in Ingram's Poe Collection, electrostatic copies 1849, 1874-1876 (Box 5)
  - Maria Clemm's letters to S. H. Whitman, annotated electrostatic copies of autograph letters and a list of the letters 1849-1859 (Box 5)
  - Poe: Anna Blackwell; various typescripts, and autograph letters ca. 1974 (Box 5)
  - Sarah Whitman's death, electrostatic copy of newsclipping 1878 (Box 5)
  - Sarah Helen Whitman's obiturary, The Athenaeum, electrostatic copy of newsclipping and annotated typescript copy 1878 July 20 (Box 5)
  - Gill's Life of Poe, The Athenaeum, electrostatic newsclipping and typescript copy 1877 Oct 6 (Box 5)
  - Gill's reply to Ingram's Review of His Life of Poe, electrostatic copies of newsclippings 1876, 1877 (Box 5)
  - Sarah Helen Whitman's Last Printed Article in The Providence Journal--"The Unpublished Correspondence of Edgar Allan Poe", photostatic copy of newsclipping 1878 May 4 (Box 5)
  - "Edgar Allan Poe's Early Poems", The Gentleman's Magazine, V. XII 1874 May, pp. 580-586, photostatic copy of article (Box 5)
  - "More New Facts About Edgar Allan Poe", The Mirror, Feb. 21, 1874, electrostatic copy and related correspondence, typed 1874, 1955, 1957, 1976 (Box 5)
  - "Edgar Poe" by John H. Ingram from Temple Bar, June 1874 v. 41, pp. 375-387 and the same reprinted from Temple Bar in The Eclectic Magazine, N.S. v. XX, August 1874, pp. 203-210 1874 (Box 5)
  - "Edgar A. Poe," Hearth and Home, VII, p. 24, photostatic copy 1895 Jan 9 (Box 5)
  - J.H.I's Review of Henry Curwen's Sorrow and Song: Studies of Literary Struggle in The Academy, pp. 262-263, electrostatic copies, annotated 1875 13 March (Box 5)
  - J.H.I.'s Review of R. G. Stoddard's Poems by Edgar Allan Poe, in Civil Service Review, electrostatic copy 1875 April 3 (Box 5)
  - Gill's Article in The Daily Graphic published without S.H.W.'s permission, electrostatic copy of newsclipping 1875 (Box 5)
  - Gill's Reply to Ingram's Disclaimer, The American Bookseller, I, 1876 Feb 15, pp. 130-131, electrostatic copy (Box 5)
  - Ingram's Rejoinder to Gill's Reply, The American Bookseller, I 1876 April 1, pp. 223-234, electrostatic copy (Box 5)
  - "Unpublished Correspondence by Edgar A. Poe," Appleton's Journal, IV, typescript w/autograph corrections and electrostatic copy 1878 May, n.d., pp. 421-429 (Box 5)
  - "The Unknown Poetry of Edgar Poe," Belgravia XXIX, photostatic copy 1876 June, pp.502-513 (Box 5)
  - "The Bibliography of Edgar Poe," all four volumes of verse, The Athenaeum, No. 2544, electrostatic copy 1876 July 29, pp. 145-146 (Box 5)
  - Illustrations for Vols. II & III, "Building Poe Biography," electrostatic copies, prints and negatives; autograph notes concerning some letters and photographs n.d. [ante 1976] (Box 5)
  - Didier's The Life and Poems of Edgar Allan Poe; and Additional Poems, in The Athenaem, No. 2572, electrostatic and typescript copies 1877 Feb 10 (Box 5)
  - Poe's "Alone" facsimile from Scribner's Monthly, electrostatic copy Sept 1875 (Box 5)
  - List of Letters from "SHW" and "JHI" and others, annotated typescript and autograph lists n.d. (Box 5)
  - "Unknown Correspondence by Edgar Poe," The New Quarterly Magazine, by John H. Ingram, electrostatic copy 1878 April, pp. 1-30 (Box 5)
  - Ingram vs. Uneda, Notes and Queries, electrostatic copy and autograph note 1876 April 22 (Box 5)
  - "The Grecian Flute," parody of "The Bells," electrostatic copy [1875] (Box 5)
  - "Portraits of Poe," by Chandos Fulton from New York Home Journal, electrostatic copy 1873 March 12 (Box 5)
  - "Poe at West Point," by Thomas W. Gibson from Harper's, electrostatic copy November, n.y. (Box 5)
  - Marie Louise Houghton's letters to S. H. Whitman, electrostatic copies of autograph letters and typescript copies 1875 May 20 (Box 5)
  - "Tormented, Tormented, Even unto Death" by Pat Lewis, The Washington Star, electrostatic copy 1977 January 17 (Box 5)
  - Letters in Vols. II and III-(Lists) autograph and typed lists n.d. (Box 5)
  - John Neal's obituary, The Athanaeum, No. 2555, mentioned in electrostatic copy 1876 Oct 14, pp. 507-508 (Box 5)
  - Susan Archer Weiss vs. Elizabeth Oakes Smith in New York Herald, electrostatic copy 1876 (Box 5)
  - E. O. Smith's article on Poe from Beadle's Monthly Magazine, electrostatic copy 1867 (Box 5)
  - Review of Ingram's and Stoddard's Biographies of Poe, The Nation, XX, electrostatic copy 1875 March 25, pp. 208-209 (Box 5)
  - Notes from the Mirror (London), autograph copies 1874 July-December (Box 5)
  - History of the Poe Monument and Dr. J. J. Moran's account of Poe's Last Hours and Death from New York Herald, electrostatic copies 1875 (Box 5)
  - "Edgar Allan Poe"-- The Daily Graphic, electrostatic copies 1875 Nov 16 (Box 5)
  - "Edgar Allan Poe," by James Purves, Dublin University Magazine, electrostatic copies 1875 March & Sept (Box 5)
  - "The Lunar Hoax," by John Ingram from The Athenaeum, typescript copy 1876 Aug 19, pp. 241-242 (Box 5)
  - "Helena Modjeska and Fanny Janauschek," Three Hundred Years of American Drama and Theatre, by Garff B. Wilson, electrostatic copies 1973 (Box 5)
  - Ingram vs. Gill, The Standard, electrostatic copy of newsclipping--"Edgar Allan Poe" by J.H.I. 1878 (Box 5)
  - "VII Stephane Mallarme and Edouard Manet Translate and Illustrate Poe's Poems" n.d. (Box 5)
  - Correspondence--Stephane Mallarme to John Ingram annotated and corrected typescript and electrostatic copies of other typescripts 1885 (Box 5)
  - Annotated Bibliography of Ingram articles about Poe; typescript copies, annotated typescript and notes 1879-1938 (Box 5)
  - "Building Poe Biography," Volume IV, electrostatic copy of autograph letters from J.H.I. 1909 (Box 5)
  - "Edgar Poe and his Biographer," Temple Bar, Vol. 68, photographic positive copy 1882 Aug, pp. 530-539 (Box 5)
  - "Edgar Poe and His Biographers," The Academy, No. 597, electrostatic copy 1883 Oct 13, pp. 248-249 (Box 5)
  - Manet's drawing of Poe with notes, photographic copy of drawing, and electrostatic copy of typed description 1849 (Box 5)
  - "Reminiscences" (of E.A.P.); "Recollections of Poe," Home Journal both by Elizabeth Oakes Smith and "Recent Biographies of Edgar A. Poe" by E. L. Didier, International Review, electrostatic copies 1876, 1881 (Box 5)
  - "Poe's Writing ' The Gold Bug' at Widow Meagher's Place," San Francisco Chronicle(?) and same from unidentified newspaper, electrostatic copy 1878 (Box 5)
  - Obituary of Stella Lewis from The Athenaeum by John H. Ingram, electrostatic copy of newsclipping [1880?] (Box 5)
  - Obituary of Louisa G. Allan, "Returned to Dust," Richmond Times-Dispatch(?), electrostatic copy of newsclipping 1881 (Box 5)
  - Poe gives Miss Susan V. C. Ingram a copy of "Ulalume," correspondence, newsclipping and transcript of poem" 1913, 1955, 1970 (Box 5)
  - "Edgar Poe and Some of His Friends," by John H. Ingram, The Bookman, electrostatic copy 1909 (Box 5)
  - "Reminiscences of Edgar A. Poe" by Mrs. Susan Archer Wiess, The Independent, v. 56, Part 2, electrostatic copy 1904 May 5, pp. 1010-1014 (Box 5)
  - "Reminiscences of Edgar Allan Poe," by Susan Archer Wiess, The Independent, electrostatic copy 1904 Aug 25 (Box 5)
  - "Edgar Allan Poe and 'Stella'," Vol. I, No. 4, The Albany Review, electrostatic 1907 July, pp. 417-423 (Box 5)
  - "Boston to Observe Centenary of Poe," The Boston Herald, and "Edgar Allan Poe," The Sunday News, Baltimore, December (?) electrostatic copies 1909 Jan 17, n.d. (Box 5)
  - "Edgar Allan Poe in Society," by Eugene L. Didier, New York Bookman, electrostatic 1909 Jan (Box 5)
  - "Edgar Allan Poe's Last Poem 'The Beautiful Physician," by John Ingram, New York Bookman, electrostatic copies 1909 Jan (Box 5)
  - "Variations in Edgar Poe's Poetry," by John H. Ingram, The Bibliophile, III, electrostatic copies 1909 May, pp. 128-136 (Box 6)
  - "The Passing of Poe's English Biographer" by J. H. Whitty, electrostatic copy 1916 (Box 6)
  - "Ingram-Discourager of Poe Biographies" by Caroline Ticknor, The New York Bookman, XLIV, electrostatic copy 1916 Sept, pp. 8-14 (Box 6)
  - Ingram's letter to Eveleth, reprinted in The Southern Magazine, XV, electrostatic copy 1874, pp. 428-430 (Box 6)
  - Notes, miscellaneous, concerning London Quarterly, annotated electrostatic copy and typescripts ca. 1976 (Box 6)
  - Obituary of Roland S. Houghton, M.D., electrostatic copy of newsclipping 1876 (Box 6)
  - Electrostatic copy, John Cook Wyllie, U. Va. Library, Rare Book Department 1955, TLS (Box 1955)
    re "Fire Fiend"
  - Information about Mrs. Sarah Helen Whitman and her sister, Anna Power, typescript and autograph notes n.d. (Box 6)
  - "The Life and Poetry of Edgar Poe" from Chambers' Journal, electrostatic copy [1853?] (Box 6)
  - "Death of Edgar A. Poe," Ludwig article, electrostatic copy 1849 (Box 6)
  - "Swinburne's Erechtheus," London Quarterly Review, electrostatic copy, and Swinburne's Letter Concerning Poe by I. B. Cauthen, Jr. 1876, 1950, printed brochure (Box 6)
  - "Edgar Allan Poe," by R. H. Stoddard, Harper's New Monthly Magazine, electrostatic copies 1872 Sept, pp. 557-568 (Box 6)
  - "Mr. Swinburne: A Sketch," by W. Winwood Reade, The Galaxy, Vol III, electrostatic copy 1867 March 15, pp. 682-684 (Box 6)
  - "Leonainie" by James Whitcomb Riley, Kokomo(Indiana) Dispatch, electrostatic copy of transcript 1877 Jul (Box 6)
  - Sarah Helen Whitman ALS to J. B. Buchanan electrostatic copy of autograph letter and annotated and corrected typescript of same 1875 (Box 6)
  - The Round Table, an electrostatic copy of an article about that journal ca. 1873 (Box 6)
  - "The Grave of Poe" by Eugene L. Didier, Appleton's, electrostatic copy 1872 Jan (Box 6)
  - "Edgar Poe," Littell's Living Age, reprinted from The Critic, vol. 41, electrostatic copy and notes 1854, pp. 166-171 (Box 6)
  - Books and magazine articles written and published by John H. Ingram other than those on Edgar Allan Poe; letter, U.Va. Library, to Miller, typescript and notes 1960, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Magazine articles and newspaper letters on persons and subjects other than Poe by John H. Ingram, typescript copies of articles, and autograph notes n.d. (Box 6)
  - Magazine articles and newspaper letters about Poe by John H. Ingram, typescript copies of articles, and autograph notes 1873-1879 (Box 6)
  - Annotated Bibliography of Books, articles, and published letters written by John H. Ingram, typescript with annotated notes n.d. (Box 6)
  - "Edgar Allan Poe,' by John H. Ingram, The International Review, Vol. II, electrostatic copies 1875 Mar, pp. 145-172 (Box 6)
  - "Poe's Suppressed Poetry," by John H. Ingram, The Daily Graphic(New York), reprinted from Belgravia, electrostatic copies 1876 Jan 8 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, electrostatic copy 1875, 1976 (Box 6)
    re: The Civil Service Review(?)
  - Poe's "Politian," The Southern Magazine, John H. Ingram, Vol. XVIII, electrostatic copies and autograph notes 1875 Nov, pp. 588-594 (Box 6)
  - "Edgar Allan Poe," by R. T. P. Allen; Scribner's Monthly, Vol. XI, electrostatic copy 1875 Nov, pp. 142-143 (Box 6)
  - Bibliographies of Edgar Poe by H. Buxton Forman, John H. Ingram, and Theodore Watts Dunton in The Athenaeum, Nos. 2545, 2547, and 2549, respectively, typescript copy and autograph notes 1876 (Box 6)
  - "A Disclaimer" by John H. Ingram, The Athenaeum, electrostatic copy and autograph notes 1876 Jan 15, p. 89 (Box 6)
  - Copies of unpublished letters from F. W. Thomas, Washington, D.C. to Edgar Allan Poe, New York and Philadelphia, typescript, carbon copy 1841-1846 (Box 6)
  - Letters, Maria Clemm to Sarah Helen Whitman, electrostatic copies annotated by John Miller 1852, 1859, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Letters from John H. Ingram to Sarah H. Whitman appearing in Poe's Helen Remembers, electrostatic copies, some annotated, of ALS 1873-1878, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - "The Man Who Put the Wreath on Poe," by Brian Phillips, electrostatic copy of a typescript filed in 5218-f 1917 (Box 6)
  - Poe Bibliography and Notes, typescript ca. 1948 (Box 6)
  - Autograph list of letters written by John H. Ingram, Maria Clemm, Sarah Helen Whitman and others, and notes n.d. (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Autograph notes and five typescript pages from: "Poe's English Biographer Concludes" by John Carl Miller, and printed matter: "Manuscripts and Publications: A Review of Recent Books" electrostatic copy and works of Edgar Allan Poe"--ARNO Press, NYC, N.Y. and Poe Studies1968-1973, n.d. (Box 6)
- Index to Poe's correspondence compiled by Miller n.d., Card tray